Mss.B.L59p
American Philosophical Society
Richard C. Lewontin papers, ca. 1963-1980
Circa 1963-1980
Mss.B.L59p
American Philosophical Society
4.0 Linear feet Ca. 2000 items
Ca. 2000 items.
This represents a portion of Lewontin's correspondence files (mainly A-L), and included are copies of papers, all of which will be added to in the future. The topics discussed in the letters are numerous, including much on contemporary scientific controversies such as race, Darwin, evolution, intelligence, and biological determinism.
Lewontin, Richard Charles, 1929-
Box 1-8
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Richard C. Lewontin and accessioned, 04/09/1979 (1979 830ms).
Biographical/Historical note
Richard C. Lewontin is a population biologist.
Existence and Location of Originals note
Holder of originals: Richard C. Lewontin.
African American History Note
Materials relating to race may be of particular interest to students of African American history.
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
Abelson, Philip Hauge Correspondence (10 items) 1975-1976
Baker, William K. Correspondence (4 items) 1974
Barker, James Stuart Flinton Correspondence (2 folders) 1971-1979
Bethel, Thomas Correspondence (13 items) 1976-1978
Calder, Nigel Correspondence (2 items) 1977
Crow, James F. Correspondence (3 folders) 1954-2002
Delbruck, Max Correspondence (6 items) 1969-1975
Dobzhansky, Theodosius Correspondence (3 folders) 1961-1998
Ehrlich, Paul R. Correspondence (2 folders) 1968-1975
Goldberger, Arthur S. Correspondence (2 folders) 1974-1978
Haldane, John Burdon Sanderson Correspondence (6 items) 1964
Hirsch, Jerry Correspondence (6 items) 1975-1977
Jacquard, Albert Correspondence (20 items) 1973-1977
Johnson, George Correspondence (3 folders) 1975-1978
Kamin, Leon J. Correspondence (5 items) 1974-1978
Krimbas, Costas B. Correspondence (3 folders) 1972-2002
Li, Ching Chun Correspondence (21 items) 1962-1978
Mayr, Ernst Correspondence (17 items) 1980-2002
Neel, James V. Correspondence (14 items) 2000
Wallace, Bruce Correspondence (2 folders) 1963-1999
Wright, Sewall Correspondence (9 items) 1959-1980
Related Archival Materials note
For additional Lewontin correspondence, see the Dobzhansky Papers (B D65), 44 items, 1961-1975; and the Dunn Papers (B D917), 28 items, 1959-1973.
Abelson, Philip Hauge; Baker, William Kaufman, 1919-; Barker, J. S. F., (James Stuart Flinton), 1931-; Bethel, Thomas; Calder, Nigel; Crow, James F. (James Franklin), 1916-; Delbrück, Max; Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich, 1900-1975; Ehrlich, Paul R.; Goldberger, Arthur Stanley, 1930-; Haldane, J. B. S. (John Burdon Sanderson), 1892-1964; Hirsch, Jerry; Jacquard, Albert; Johnson, George; Kamin, Leon J.; Krimbas, Costas B.; Biology, genetics, eugenics; Evolution.; Genetics.; Intellect.; Race, race relations, racism; Race.
- Selected Inventory from Genetics Subject Guide
  - Abelson, Philip Hauge, 1975-1976; Correspondence ( 10 items )
    Beckwith, Jonathan R.; Biographical and personal data; Davis, Bernard; Editorial matters; Human genetics -- Race; Political issues; Publication -- Science; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Baker, William K., 1974; Correspondence ( 4 items )
    Drosophila genetics; National Science Foundation; Population genetics; Research support
  - Barker, James Stuart Flinton, 1971-1979; Correspondence ( 2 folders )
    Bibliographical matters; Biographical and personal data; Drosophila genetics; Fellowships, assistantships; Population genetics; Recommendations; University of Sydney
  - Bethel, Thomas, 1976-1978; Correspondence ( 13 items )
    American Museum of Natural History; Darwin, Charles; Evolution; Genetics; Lamarck, Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet de; Lectures, public speaking; Political issues -- Social Darwinism; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Calder, Nigel, 1977; Correspondence ( 2 items )
    Publication -- Horizon; Sociobiology
  - Crow, James F., 1954-2002; Correspondence ( 3 folders )
    American Institute of Biological Sciences; Behavioral genetics, IQ; Conferences and symposia; Congratulations, greetings, thanks -- National Academy of Sciences; Dobzhansky, Theodosius; Evolution; Honors -- University of Chicago; Human genetics; Jensen, Arthur Robert; Kempthorne, Oscar; Kimura, Motoo; Lectures, public speaking; Muller, Hermann Joseph; Political issues; Population genetics; Russian politics and science; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics; Vavilov, Nikolai Ivanovich
  - Delbruck, Max, 1969-1975; Correspondence ( 6 items )
    Behavioral genetics, IQ; Cogan, Alex; Ethical issues; Evolution; Lectures, public speaking -- Nova; National Academy of Sciences; Population genetics; Russian politics and science
  - Dobzhansky, Theodosius, 1961-1998; Correspondence ( 3 folders )
    Behavioral genetics, IQ; Biographical and personal data; Columbia University; Cordeiro, Antonio R.; Crow, James F.; Drosophila genetics; Ethical issues; Evolution; Human genetics; Kimura, Motoo; Krimbas, Costas B.; Laboratory techniques, equipment; Lectures, public speaking; Lectures, public speaking -- Behavioral Genetics Association; Lerner, Isadore Michael; Li, Ching Chun; Molecular genetics; National Academy of Sciences; Political issues; Population genetics; Publication; Russian politics and science; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs; Spassky, Boris; Stone, Wilson Stuart; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Wallace, Bruce; Zoology
  - Ehrlich, Paul R., 1968-1975; Correspondence ( 2 folders )
    Pearson, Karl; Population genetics; Publication -- BioScience; Smith, Dean O.; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Ware, James H.
  - Goldberger, Arthur S., 1974-1978; Correspondence ( 2 folders )
    Becker, Gary; Behavioral genetics, IQ; Burt, Cyril Lodowic, Sir; Eugenics; Genetics of plants; Human genetics; Human genetics -- Race; Jensen, Arthur Robert; Requests for reprints; Reviews -- Kamin, Leon J.; Thomas, Hoben; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Haldane, John Burdon Sanderson, 1964; Correspondence ( 6 items )
    Biographical and personal data; Human genetics; Mouse genetics; Political issues; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Hirsch, Jerry, 1975-1977; Correspondence ( 6 items )
    Behavioral genetics, IQ; Crow, James F.; Dobzhansky, Theodosius; Human genetics -- Race; Publication -- Science; Reviews -- Behavior Genetics; Shockley, William
  - Jacquard, Albert, 1973-1977; Correspondence ( 20 items )
    Behavioral genetics, IQ; Feldman, Marcus; Human genetics -- Race; Invitations; Population genetics; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Johnson, George, 1975-1978; Correspondence ( 3 folders )
    Behavioral genetics, IQ; Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Chovnick, Arthur; Drosophila genetics; Feldman, Marcus; Lectures, public speaking; Peacock, William James; Population genetics; Recommendations; Referee's report; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Kamin, Leon J., 1974-1978; Correspondence ( 5 items )
    Behavioral genetics, IQ; Human genetics -- Twins
  - Krimbas, Costas B., 1972-2002; Correspondence ( 3 folders )
    Academic freedom; Biographical and personal data; Drosophila genetics; Fellowships, assistantships -- Harvard; Genetics of plants; Human genetics; Philosophy of science; Political issues -- Greece; Population genetics; Referee's report; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Li, Ching Chun, 1962-1978; Correspondence ( 21 items )
    Crow, James F.; Dobzhansky, Theodosius; Kimura, Motoo; Lectures, public speaking; Population genetics; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics
  - Mayr, Ernst, 1980-2002; Correspondence ( 17 items )
    Bacterial genetics; Bacteriophage and viral genetics; Biographical and personal data; Darwin, Charles; Evolution; Population genetics; Publication; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Vorontsov, Nikolai
  - Neel, James V., 2000; Correspondence ( 14 items )
    Anthropology; Atomic Energy Commission; Biographical and personal data; Ethical issues; Eugenics; Population genetics; Publication -- Darkness in El Dorado; Radiation genetics; Tierney, Patrick; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Wallace, Bruce, 1963-1999; Correspondence ( 2 folders )
    Crow, James F.; Dobzhansky, Theodosius; Drosophila genetics; Evolution; Kimura, Motoo; McClintock, Barbara; National Academy of Sciences; Population genetics; Recommendations; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics; Tan, C. C.; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Wright, Sewall, 1959-1980; Correspondence ( 9 items )
    Congratulations, greetings, thanks -- National Medal of Science; Drosophila genetics; Evolution; Fisher, Ronald Aylmer